Guide to the Archives of Irish America Collection on the Gaelic Athletic Association (GAA) of New York AIA.028
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Archives of Irish America Collection on the Gaelic Athletic Association (GAA) of New York
1934-2005
1980-2000
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Archives of Irish America
AIA.028
2 Linear Feet in 4 manuscript boxes and 1 folder in shared housing
The Gaelic Athletic Association (GAA) was established in Ireland in 1884 as a part of the Gaelic Revival as a way to encourage the playing of Gaelic football and hurling. Gaelic games had been played in America since the Irish first emigrated, but play was not standardized until enthusiasts in New York formed the city's first GAA Board in 1914. They also sought to organize games with teams in other cities along the East Coast. The collection contains programs, fliers, clippings, photographs, and publications by and of the Gaelic Athletic Association, specifically regarding the playing of hurling and football at the three fields in the New York area in the middle of the twentieth century.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains programs, fliers, clippings, photographs, and publications by and of the Gaelic Athletic Association, specifically regarding the playing of hurling and football at the three fields in the New York area in the middle of the twentieth century.
Arrangement
Files are arranged alphabetically.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Dorothy Hayden Cudahy Irish Memories Collection AIA 001
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical Note
The Gaelic Athletic Association (GAA) was established in Ireland in 1884 as a part of the Gaelic Revival as a way to encourage the playing of Gaelic football and hurling. Local chapters were opened in Ireland and America throughout the late nineteenth and twentieth centuries. While Gaelic games had been played in America since the Irish first emigrated, play was not fully standardized until enthusiasts in New York formed the city's first GAA Board in 1914. They also sought to organize games with teams in other cities along the East Coast. There were three fields of note in New York City for much of the twentieth century: Celtic Park in Queens, the Polo Grounds in Upper Manhattan, and Gaelic Park (a.k.a. Croke Park) in the Bronx.
One of the highlights for the New York GAA was the 1947 All-Ireland Gaelic Football Final between Cavan and Kerry. Played at the Polo Grounds, it is the only All-Ireland final played outside of Ireland. It was held in New York to commemorate 100th anniversary of the worst year of the Great Famine, and the thousands of Irish who came to New York as a consequence.
Interest in football and hurling is dependent upon immigration from Ireland and there was a slump in the 1970s. However, the 1980s revived the local GAA, as the influx of undocumented Irish brought with it new players.
Custodial History
The bulk of the material comprising this collection was part of a larger donation given by Dorothy Hayden Cudahy to the Archives of Irish America in 1995. In addition, printed material in the collection has been gathered by Archives of Irish America staff from various sources, including other collections at the Archives of Irish America. The accession number associated with this collection is 1997.052.
In March 2025, Marion Casey donated an accretion of photographs and photocopied newspaper clippings; the accession number associated with this transfer is 2025.026.
Irish Americans -- New York (N.Y.); Clippings (information artifacts); Gaelic football.; Correspondence.; Fliers (printed matter); Irish Americans -- New York (N.Y.) -- Social life and customs.; Programs (documents); Black-and-white photographs.; Cudahy, John J., 1920-1994; Gaelic Athletic Association
- All-Ireland Camogie: USA Tour, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- The Astoria Gaels Social and Football Club, 1997-1999 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Brooklyn Shamrocks Football Club, 1992, 2000-2001 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Connemara Gaels Football Club of New York, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Emerald Golf Society of Greater New York, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Gaelic Athletic Association All-Ireland Finals, 1952-1989 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Gaelic Athletic Association Correspondence and Minutes, 1944, 1946, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Gaelic Athletic Association Financial Statements, 1954-1961 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Gaelic Athletic Association of Greater New York Annual Banquet, 1962-1969 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Gaelic Athletic Association of Greater New York Annual Banquet, 1973-1979 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Gaelic Athletic Association of Greater New York Annual Banquet, 1990-1992 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Gaelic Athletic Association of Greater New York Annual Banquet, 1982-1989 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Gaelic Athletic Association of Greater New York Annual Banquet, 1994-1999 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Gaelic Athletic Association of Greater New York Game Programs, 1951-1959 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Gaelic Athletic Association of Greater New York Game Programs, 1962-1969 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Gaelic Athletic Association of Greater New York Game Programs, 1974-1979 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Gaelic Athletic Association of Greater New York Game Programs, 1980-1990 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Gaelic Athletic Association New York Board: "The New York Irish", 1976 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Gaelic Athletic Association New York Ladies Dinner Dance, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Gaelic Athletic Association New York Minor Board All-Ireland Gaels, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Gaelic Athletic Association New York Minor Board Banquet and Championship Awards, 1989, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Gaelic Athletic Association New York Minor Board Banquet and Championship Awards, 1997, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Gaelic Athletic Association New York Minor Board Fall Dinner Dance, 1994-1995, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Gaelic Athletic Association New York Minor Board Schedule of Games, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Gaelic Athletic Association of New York World Cup Championship, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Gaelic Athletic Association Press Releases and Clippings, 1957-1989, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Gaelic Athletic Association Team Photographs, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Gaelic Athletic Association Ticket Stubs, 1957-1959 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Gaelic Athletic Association USA Tour: Ballina Stephenites, County Mayo, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Gaelic Athletic Association USA Tour: Financial Statements, 1954, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Gaelic Athletic Association USA Tour: Kilmeena, County Mayo, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Good Sheperd Gaelic Football Club, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Ladies Gaelic Football Association of New York, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- The New England Gaelic Athletic Association, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- New York Celtics Gaelic Football Club, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- New York Young Ireland's Camogie Club, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- New York Young Ireland's Camogie Club, 1990-1992 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- North American Camogie Association, 1994-1995 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Photographs and Photocopied Newspaper Clippings, 1934-1955 (Box Shared Tamiment 193, Folder 4)
- Randall's Island Gaelic Sports Complex, Inc., circa 2005 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Rangers Gaelic Football Club of New York Dinner/Dance Journal, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Saint Barnabas Gaelic Football Club, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- St. Jerome's Gaelic Football Club, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 12)